"Natural Dietary Remedy for Insomnia"
There is a perception that time
spent asleep is time wasted,
but it is widely recognized that
inadequate sleep is associated
with multiple acute
and chronic conditions,
and results in the increased
risk of death and disease.
Force people to go one week with
only six hours of sleep a night,
and you can change expression
of more than 700 genes.
The most dire effect may
be endothelial dysfunction.
The endothelium is the thin layer of
cells that covers the internal surface
of blood vessels and is responsible
for allowing our arteries
to relax and dilate
back open properly.
Randomize people for about a week
to get five rather than seven hours
of sleep, and just that two-hour
difference a night resulted
in a significant impairment
in artery function.
Okay, but what do these numbers mean?
How bad is a week of 5-hour nights?
Sleep deprivation is no joke.
The magnitude of impairment is similar
to that reported in people who smoke,
have diabetes, or have
coronary artery disease.
No wonder people who sleep less than
seven hours a night may experience
a 12% to 35% increased
risk of premature death
compared to those who
get a full seven hours.
Yet a significant proportion
of the population may
routinely get less than that.
Sufficiently long, restful
sleep sessions each night
are said to be an indisputable
cornerstone of good health.
Okay, so what can we do about it?
Those who have sleep apnea,
a common consequence of obesity
that interferes with sleep, benefit
from the use of CPAP machines
while they're losing the weight to treat
the underlying cause, hopefully.
But what if apnea isn't your problem?
What if you just have trouble
falling asleep or staying asleep?
In my book How Not to Diet, I have a
whole section on sleep enhancement,
where I go through the Four
Rules of Sleep Conditioning
and the Four Rules
of Sleep Hygiene.
What if you follow those guidelines
but still can't get to sleep?
Any natural dietary remedies?
I already have videos on using
kiwifruit to fight insomnia,
and tart cherries, too.
Are there any vegetables
that might help?
Lactuca sativa is a plant that
has been traditionally used
in the treatment of insomnia.
What is this exotic sounding
leafy vegetable? Lettuce!
Evidently lettuce extracts have been
used from the time of the Roman Empire
as agents with sedative and
sleep-inducing properties.
Lettuce actually does have a hypnotic
substance in it called lactucin,
which is what makes
lettuce taste a little bitter.
But you don't know if it actually
works until you put it to the test.
And it works...in toads.
But it also works in rodents.
Sleep in both mice and rats
is enhanced by romaine lettuce.
They used romaine since
it has a higher lactucin content
compared to other lettuces.
Okay, but does it work in people?
About 10 years ago, a study was
published in which insomnia sufferers
were randomized to receive lettuce seed
oil, oil extracted from lettuce seeds.
Within a week, about 70% of those
in the lettuce seed oil group
said their insomnia very much
or much improved,
compared to only 20% in
the placebo control group.
The researchers concluded that lettuce
seed oil was found to be a useful,
safe sleeping aid in geriatric patients
suffering from sleeping difficulties.
They chose to study older individuals
because insomnia affects surprisingly
20 to 40% of older adults
at least a few nights a month.
You think that's bad. Sleep
disturbances can plague as many
as nearly 8 out of 10 women
during pregnancy.
Of course, there's lots
of different sleeping pills,
but they may endanger
the fetus or mother.
For example, doctors frequently
prescribe Ambien for pregnant women
who have trouble sleeping, but Ambien
use is associated with a wide range
of adverse pregnancy outcomes
like low birth weight babies,
premature birth, and cesarean section.
And the use of valium during
pregnancy has been linked
to birth defects
including limb deficiencies.
There has to be a better way.
What about trying lettuce?
The lettuce oil study had
a number of limitations.
For example, it was only single-blind,
meaning the researchers knew
who was on the lettuce supplements
and who was on placebo,
which could have introduced some bias.
But the researchers essentially said,
"Give us a break. Big pharma
has billions to spend on research.
No one wants to fund
studies on lettuce."
Finally, we got a double-blind,
placebo-controlled study,
but this time on a whole food,
not just a lettuce seed extract.
Yeah, but how do you come
up with a placebo lettuce?
How are you going to hide who
gets lettuce and who doesn't?
Well, you can't fit a head
of lettuce into a capsule,
but you can fit whole lettuce seeds.
And here we go: a double-blind
randomized placebo-controlled trial
on lettuce seeds for
pregnancy-related insomnia.
A hundred pregnant women
with insomnia were randomized
to receive capsules containing
either a quarter teaspoon
of ground lettuce seeds or
a placebo for two weeks,
and those on the lettuce seeds
saw a significant improvement
in a sleep quality index score
compared to placebo
with no reported side effects.